Finding Aid for Matthaei Botanical Gardens (University of Michigan) publications 1928-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Matthaei Botanical Gardens (University of Michigan) publications 1928-2005, 1970-2005
University of Michigan. Matthaei Botanical Gardens.
2 linear feet
Established in 1897, the Matthaei Botanical Gardens serves as an educational resource for the university and local community. The publications cover the published and printed material produced by the Matthaei Botanical Gardens and its sub-units. In 2004, the Matthaei Botanical Gardens merged with the Nichols Arboretum. The publications produced after the units combined can be found in the Matthaei Botanical Gardens and Nichols Arboretum collections.
978 Bimu C26 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Publications are received periodically from the unit (donor no. 6701 ).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The records are open for research.
At the time of the founding of the University of Michigan in 1817, administrators provided for the establishment of a "Botanic Garden." However, it was not until 1897 that the gardens were established. At that time, they served as an adjunct of the Department of Botany and the College of Pharmacy, located on the central campus. When this location proved to be inadequate, professors Frederick C. Newcombe and Volney M. Spaulding attempted to obtain a new site.
In 1906, Professor Newcombe successfully secured twenty-seven acres of land, located between Geddes Avenue and the Huron River, from Dr. and Mrs. Walter H. Nichols. In order to enlarge this property, George P. Burns, later the first director of the gardens, acquired twenty-five acres of adjoining property from the city of Ann Arbor and another thirty acres from the Detroit Edison Company.
The new "Botanical Gardens and Arboretum" existed under the jurisdiction of the Department of Botany, of which Director Burns was a staff member. Burns' appointment as director began in 1907 and ended in 1910, at which time he left Ann Arbor to head the Department of Botany at the University of Vermont. After several acting directors, Henry Allan Gleason became director and served from 1915 to 1919.
Dissatisfaction with the Geddes area site arose around 1913, because the land was not flat enough for experimental gardens. President Hutchins reorganized the administration of the gardens by creating a "committee of management," who purchased an additional twenty acres of land in 1914, near Packard Road beyond the city limits. This site later became known as the "Iroquois Site." The Department of Botany and College of Pharmacy utilized this site, while the Departments of Landscape Design and Forestry continued their use of the Geddes site. The latter eventually became the Nichols Arboretum.
Harley Henry Bartlett succeeded Gleason in 1919, and soon President Hutchins once again reorganized the administration of the gardens. The Botanical Gardens became an autonomous department in the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts. Although the Department of Botany was to have no control over gardens policies or budgets, the gardens directorship was to be filled by a faculty member from the department.
The "Iroquois Site" remained the location of the Botanical Gardens through Bartlett's tenure as director, which ended in 1955. Bartlett was succeeded by A. Geoffrey Norman. As the rapidly developing city of Ann Arbor encroached on the site, it became an unsuitable location for the gardens. To remedy the situation in 1957, Mr. and Mrs. Fredrick C. Matthaei gave approximately 250 acres of land near Dixboro, to which the university added an additional 100 acres. The dedication took place on June 14, 1962, and in 1969 the property was renamed the Matthaei Botanical Gardens in honor of the donors.
After the move, several important facilities, such as a conservatory, greenhouses and classrooms, were built through three-phased construction from 1959 to 1965. With the increase in facilities and the expanded availability of natural areas, research and teaching opportunities at the Gardens considerably expanded.
Dr. Warren H. Wagner, Jr. succeeded Dr. Norman as director in 1966, and Professor Erich E. Steiner succeeded Dr. Wagner in 1971. In 1974, during Steiner's tenure, the Gardens' membership program, "Friends of the Matthaei Botanical Gardens," was established. This group, comprised of Ann Arbor area residents, conducts annual fund drives for the gardens. Steiner resigned in 1977 and was replaced by Professor William S. Benninghoff, who had been very active in the development of the Dixboro site. He was later succeeded by Catherine Bach (1985-1987); Anton Reznicek (1987-1989); Erich Steiner (1971-1977, 1989-1991); William S. Benninghoff (1977-1986); Catherine Bach as Acting Director (1986-1987); Anton A. Reznicek (1987-1989); Patricia Hopkinson as Acting Director (1991-1994); James A. Teeri (1994-2002); and Brian J. Klatt as Interim Director (2002-2004).
The Gardens typically have over 30 research projects conducted each year by University of Michigan and non-University of Michigan researchers. In addition, the Gardens provides plant material for U-M courses and is the site for regular classes or field trips for approximately 20 classes from U-M and six other colleges and universities. In addition to research, thousands of visitors come to the Conservatory and grounds each year to participate in adult education courses, volunteer activities, and special events or just to visit the grounds. Two auxiliary organizations that are vital to the success of these programs are the Friends of the Matthaei Botanical Gardens, founded in 1974, and the Docents, who were formally organized in 1982.
In 2003, the associate provost Janet Weiss explored the possibility of combining the Botanical Gardens and the Arboretum. In 2004 the two units were united as a single independent unit of the University of Michigan. In 2007, the Botanical Gardens celebrated its 100 year anniversary. A separate records group for Nichols Arboretum is available at the Bentley Historical Library.
Further information can be found in the Matthaei Botanical Gardens and Nichols Arboretum collection, which covers the records of the units after they combined.
The record group Matthaei Botanical Gardens (University of Michigan) Publications contains a variety of publications produced by the Botanical Gardens, including annual reports, brochures and pamphlets, bulletins, histories, manuals and guidebooks, newsletters, and reports as well more ephemeral items such as event programs and flyers. The Publications of the Matthaei Botanical Gardens are divided into three series: Unit Publications, Sub-Unit Publications, and Topical Publications.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor Flower and Garden Show.; University of Michigan. Matthaei Botanical Gardens.; University of Michigan. Matthaei Botanical Gardens. Friends.; University of Michigan. Matthaei Botanical Gardens. Adult Education Program.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Matthaei Botanical Gardens. Adult Education Program.; University of Michigan. Matthaei Botanical Gardens. Friends.; Matthaei Botanical Gardens.; Ann Arbor Flower and Garden Show.
Genre/Form:
Annual reports.; Bulletins.; Histories.; Manuals.; Newsletters.; Pamphlets.; Reports.
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series contains printed material published specifically by the Matthaei Botanical Gardens. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of the publication. This includes annual reports relating to the development of the Matthaei Botanical Gardens during the 1980s and brochures describing the conservatory, endangered plants in Michigan, tour information, and wildflowers. The bulletin Bartlettia explains the origins and uses of plants in the specialized gardens. This series also contains histories, manuals describing the various plants in the permanent collection, and reports detailing plans for development of the Matthaei Botanical Garden site. Press releases from 1983 to 1995 describe various exhibits and displays mounted by staff and volunteers and lectures sponsored by the Matthaei Botanical Gardens.
  - Annual Reports
    - Annual Report 1983-1984 (Box 1)
    - Annual Report, 1996-1997, 1997-1998, 1999-2000 (Box 1)
    - Annual Report, 2001-2002, 2002-2003 (Reports continue in the separate Matthaei Botanical Gardens and Nichols Arboretum collection) (Box 1)
    - Six Year Report, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Articles
    - "Ferns and Spores" by Walter Kleinschmidt (Box 1)
    - General (Box 1)
    - "Land Available to Zoologists" compiled by the Brownian Movement 1967 (Box 1)
    - "The Nature and Role of University and College Affiliated Botanical Gardens and Arboreta" by Erich Steiner undated (Box 1)
    - "Poisonous Plants" by David C. Michner, Roger Keller and Robert F. Kowalski 1992 (Box 1)
    - "Orchids" proposal by Kerry Walter 1979 (Box 1)
    - Secondary Articles (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - Celebrate the Seasons With Wildflowers, undated, and The American Horticultural Society 2001 Reciprocal Gardens, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Conservatory, undated (Box 1)
    - Deconstructed Landscapes, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Education Publications, 1999-2005 (Box 1)
    - Endowment (Box 1)
    - Epiphyte, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Events, scattered (Box 1)
    - Gateway to the Gardens (Box 1)
    - General Brochures (Box 1)
    - General Tour Information (Box 1)
    - Matteson Barn (Box 1)
    - Michigan's Plants in Danger (Box 1)
    - Perennial Garden Kids Brochure, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Sculpture at Matthaei undated (Box 1)
    - See How Our Gardens Grow, 1995 and undated (Box 1)
    - Trail Brochures (Box 1)
    - Youth and Family Classes, 2001-2002 (Box 1)
  - Bulletins
    - Bartlettia: Notes from the Matthaei Botanical Gardens of the University of Michigan, 1975-1982, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Calendars of Events 1998, undated (Box 1)
  - Educational Activities Materials
    - Passport to Africa 2000 (Box 1)
  - Events
    - People, Plants and Cultures (Box 1)
  - Fact Sheets undated (Box 1)
  - Flyers undated (Box 1)
  - Histories
    - Botanical Gardens, undated (Box 1)
    - The Botanical Gardens by Harley H. Bartlett, undated (Box 1)
    - Frederick Charles Newcombe, 1858-1927 by J.B. Pollock and H.H. Bartlett, 1928 (Box 1)
    - Future Use of Old Botanical Gardens by Leonard K Eaton, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Not Just Botany: Research at the Matthaei Botanical Gardens, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Research at the Matthaei Botanical Gardens, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Invitations
    - Dedicatory Exercises 1962 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1996-2001 (Box 1)
    - Volunteer Appreciation Events 1989-1996, undated (Box 1)
  - Lists
    - Birds Observed at the Matthaei Botanical Gardens of the University of Michigan, undated (Box 1)
    - Plants in Permanent Collection (Box 1)
  - Manuals
    - Along the Way...A Guide to the Nature Trails, undated (Box 1)
    - Brief Guide to the Trails undated (Box 1)
    - Guide to the Matthaei Botanical Gardens, 1986, undated (Box 1)
    - Plants in the Permanent Collection, undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Tours undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Trail Guides, 1985, 1992, undated (Box 1)
    - A Narrative Guide to Parker Brooks Trail, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Out of Africa Self-Guided Tour undated (Box 1)
    - A Self-Guided Tour of the Matthaei Botanical Gardens Conservatory undated (Box 1)
    - Trails in the Matthaei Botanical Gardens, undated (Box 1)
    - Trails of the Matthaei Botanical Gardens, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Your Guide to the Conservatory 1998 (Box 1)
  - Maps (Box 1)
  - Newsletters
    - A Blast to the Past, 1999 (Box 1)
    - News of the Gardens, for the Gardens..., 1995-2000 (Box 1)
    - News, General, scattered (Box 1)
  - Post Cards (Box 1)
  - Press Releases
    - 1983-1984 undated (Box 1)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - 1988-1995 (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - Botanical Gardens Buildings--Phase 3 (May 1966-May 1970), 1970 (Box 1)
    - Guide to Future Development: Matthaei Botanical Gardens/Radrick Farm, 1983 (Box 1)
    - Master Plan, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Proposal to Combine with the Exhibit Museum of Natural History, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Report on Hybrids of American Wild Rose Species at the Botanical Gardens at Ann Arbor, Michigan 1961 (Box 2)
  - Special Publications
    - Winter Wildflowers (Box 2)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  The Sub-Unit Publications series contains publications from subordinate offices, departments, programs and organizations within the Matthaei Botanical Gardens. These publications are arranged alphabetically by the creating sub-unit. The Ann Arbor Flower and Garden Show programs and the Herb Study Group brochures are also included in this series. There is an almost complete run of the Friends of the Matthaei Botanical Gardens newsletter under the various titles: Friends of the Matthaei Botanical Gardens Newsletter (10 vol.) published from 1974 to 1984; Newsletter (7 vol.) produced from 1985 to 1991; Matthaei Botanical Gardens (7 vol.) published from 1991 to 1998; and Cuttings which was first issued in 1998.
  - Adult Education Program
    - Calendars 1992-2002 (Box 2)
  - Ann Arbor Flower and Garden Show
    - Programs 1990-1998, 9 folders (Box 2)
    - Schedules 1998 (Box 2)
  - Docents
    - Brochures 1984-1990 (Box 2)
    - Invitations
      - Graduation Celebrations 1989-1991, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Newsletters
      - Guidelines, 1983-1997, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Friends of the Matthaei Botanical Gardens
    - Brochures
      - Membership 1994-2001, undated (Box 2)
      - We Need You!, undated (Box 2)
    - Bulletins
      - Friends News Bulletin, 1995 (Box 2)
    - Flyers
      - Gift Shop Grand Opening 1986 (Box 2)
      - Lectures 1990, 1993, 1997-2002 (Box 2)
      - Plant sales 1979-1999, undated (Box 2)
    - Histories
      - Friends of the Matthaei Botanical Gardens--The First Decade, by Helen V. Smith, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Invitations 1990
      - Annual and Special Meetings 1987, 1998, 2001, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Newsletters
      - Friends of the Matthaei Botanical Gardens Newsletter, 1974-1984 vol. 1-10, 10 folders (Box 2)
      - Newsletter, vol. 11-17, 1985-1991, 7 folders (Box 2)
      - Matthaei Botanical Gardens, vol. 18-24, 1991-1998, 7 folders (Box 2)
      - Cuttings: For the Members and Supporters of the University of Michigan Matthaei Botanical Gardens, 1998-2003, 4 folders (Box 2)
        (continues as the Friends of Matthaei Botanical Gardens and Nichols Arboretum newsletter in the separate Matthaei Botanical Gardens and Nichols Arboretum collection)
      - Herb Study Group (Box 2)
    - Brochures and Flyers 1997-1998, undated (Box 2)
  - Writer's Camp in Action 1997-1998 (Box 2)